Brian Howell

NUMERICAL OPTIMIZATION · PHYSICS SIMULATION · HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING

6102 Etcheverry Berkeley, California 94720

■ bhowell@berkeley.edu | ♣ bmhowell.github.io | ☑ bmhowell | 届 https://www.linkedin.com/in/howellbrian/





Summary _____

I am interested in applications for high performance computing. I specialize in numerical optimization applied to physics-based simulations. I write custom solvers and ML algorithms from scratch in C++ and Python, and have experience in writing low-level parallel code in CUDA and OpenMP.

Education

University of California, Berkeley

PhD in Multi-physics simulation and optimization

PHD IN MULTI-PHYSICS SIMULATION AND OPTIMIZA

- · Advisor: Tarek Zohdi
- · Dissertation Title: Physics-Informed Machine Learning and Optimization for Advanced Manufacturing

University of California, Berkeley

MSc in Mechanical Engineering

Brigham Young University

BSc in Chemical Engineering

Berkeley, California Aug 2019 - May 2024 (expected)

Berkeley, California

Aug 2019 - Dec 2021

Provo, Utah

Jan 2013 - April 2017

Experience

Google X, the moonshot factory

AI RESIDENT: materials optimization, physics simulation, & machine learning

Mountain View, California

Jan. 2022 - Dec. 2022

• Machine Learning/Optimization: Gaussian processes + Bayesian optimization, deep neural networks, convex optimization

- Physics Simulation/Modeling: Discrete element method, convex geometry
- Hardware: Sensor development and data processing, high-throughput experimentation, feedback control systems for complex fluid flow.
- Publicly Available Output: Two patent applications (one as lead inventor)

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Livermore, California

May 2017 - Jan. 2022

- Software/Simulation: Controllers, sensors, toolpath generation and optimization, digital twins for extrusion and curing
- Hardware/Chemical: Hardware integration, CAD modeling & design, chemical formulation
- Testing: Rheology & UV kinetics, mechanical (Instron), Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM)
- Publicly Available Output: Two patents, one publication, work featured in Advanced Science News.

University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, California

Jan. 2021 - Dec. 2021

GRADUATE STUDENT INSTRUCTOR (GSI)

STAFF SCIENTIST/ENGINEER: 3D printing

- Head GSI: Modeling and Simulation of Advanced Manufacturing Processes Professor Tarek Zohdi
 Received UC Berkeley Outstanding GSI Award
- Micro Course TA: Robust Optimization and Applications Professor Laurent El Ghaoui
- Head GSI: Modeling and Simulation Tools for Industrial Research Applications Professor Tarek Zohdi

Zucrow Propulsion Lab, Purdue University

West Lafayette, Indiana

RESEARCH ASSISTANT: energetic materials

June 2016 - Aug. 2016

• Formulation: Developed methods for modulating ignition sensitivity in propellants via piezoelectric polymers and varying electric fields.

Relevant Graduate Coursework

Dynamic Optimization \cdot Robust Optimization \cdot Convex Optimization 1/2 \cdot Machine Learning Tools for Energy Transport \cdot Bayesian Analysis and Machine Learning for Physicists \cdot Deep Reinforcement Learning, Decision Making, and Control \cdot Numerical Solutions to ODEs/PDEs 1/2 \cdot Finite Element Method \cdot Modeling and Simulation of Advanced Manufacturing Processes \cdot Parallel Computing \cdot Quantitative Finance

Skills

Programming Tools Python · PyTorch · C++ · OpenMP · CUDA

Computational Methods Numerical Methods · Convex opt. · Derivative-free opt. · Machine learning